This video will give you a full and
complete guide to fine-tuning LLMs on
your own hardware. What I'm going to
show you how to do here is pick the
correct LLM, fine-tune it based on your
own data, and then use it and compare it
to the existing base models so you can
see if it's actually working. I'm going
to give you a full guide. I'm going to
explain everything. I'm going to walk
through a full tutorial, so by the end
of this video, you understand everything
and you can fine-tune your own models.
With that said, let's dive in. Okay. So,
first thing, let's just talk a little
bit about fine-tuning in general, then
we'll dive into the tool that we're
going to use, and we'll start going
through the tutorial. Now, the basic
idea behind fine-tuning is that rather
than us building our own LLM completely
from scratch, which is super complicated
and it's going to require a massive
amount of hardware, we take an existing
LLM, one that's already pretty good, and
we just add our own data to it. We just
take a bunch of examples, and we
essentially train that on top of the
base LLM. So, this would allow us to
have an example like what we see on
screen, where we have an LLM that's
already good at language, can already
form sentences. So, for example, maybe
it replies like this, and then we train
it based on some of our own examples,
and it will kind of populate here in a
second, and we get a custom version
that's fit to our specific domain. So,
for example, a Tim llama model, right,
that talks like me. That's something
that's very easy to make, which you're
going to see. Now, in order to do this,
we're going to use a tool called Unsloth
Studio. Now, Unsloth Studio is a new
release or a new kind of tool from
Unsloth themselves, which I believe is
built and maintained by Nvidia
engineers. Now, the idea is that Unsloth
Studio is a graphical user interface on
top of the pre-existing and very popular
tool called Unsloth. Unsloth was
typically command-line based, meaning
you need to write a bunch of commands in
the terminal, a little bit complicated
to use. They've now built a really nice
graphical user interface, which they're
calling the studio, which allows you to
do everything just from a graphical user
interface. So, we get a full web user
interface for fine-tuning. This is free,
open source, you don't need an account,
and you don't even have to be connected
to the internet. It runs completely on
your machine, and then you can download
and fine-tune pretty much any open
source model that you want, and it runs
extremely fast because it's using some
pretty optimized software in the
background, which can then utilize your
GPU, CPU, RAM, memory, all of the stuff
that you have on your machine much
faster than if you were to try to train
it yourself. Okay.
Let's keep going. In this UI, just so
you can understand, we can fine-tune the
model. We can also build the data sets,
which is arguably even more important,
and then we can ship and package up and
export the model if we want to share it
with other people. All right, so let's
quickly just talk about kind of the
mechanics of fine-tuning, the methods
that we can use, and then I want to get
into the demo. Now, like I said, the
basic idea with fine-tuning is that we
keep a base model. We add a bunch of our
own examples to it. These are going to
be in kind of a data set that we create.
We then train what's called a LoRA
adapter layer that's kind of on top of,
or I don't know, outside of or next to
the base model, and that combined gives
us our specialized model. So, if we have
a look at a quick diagram here, you can
see that we actually don't touch the
base model at all. So, let's say we pick
a Llama 8 billion parameter model. We
don't touch the base weights or the base
model itself. What we do instead is we
train what's called this LoRA adapter
layer. You don't need to worry too much
about exactly what that means. It's less
than 1% of the size of the actual base
model itself, and what will happen is
we'll kind of add these layers on top of
the base model, and it will allow us to
kind of steer or fine-tune the output
from this model. So, I'm giving you a
really, really high-level explanation,
but we're not touching the base itself.
We're just training these kind of
additional layers on top, and these
additional layers help to fine-tune or
adjust or tweak or push the model's
output in the right direction so it gets
closer to our examples and the output
that we're looking for. Okay? So, just
understand that and by doing this it
allows us to really optimize the
training process and to keep the model
size very small without having to train
a bunch of different weights.
Okay. Let's keep going and quickly talk
about QLoRA. Now, when you do this
fine-tuning, there's many different
methods you can use. You can use LoRA
adapters, you can use QLoRA adapters,
and the one that we're going to use and
which is recommend is QLoRA. Now, when
you see QLoRA, this is effectively the
exact same thing as what I just
explained. The only difference is we're
using a compressed version of the base
model. So, by default, the models are in
a format where we have 16-bit weights.
That means we're using 16 bits of
information for every single weight,
which makes these models quite large.
So, for example, our base model might be
16 GB. Rather than keeping the full 16
GB model, which is going to take up a
ton of room in our video memory, we can
quantize it and compress it down to a
4-bit format. This will then shrink it
drastically so you can see it goes from
about 16 GB down to 5, 6, 7 GB, and then
we can fit all of that in our memory
plus the training that we do for these
adapter layers so that the overall size
that we need or the overall RAM that we
need is much smaller than if we were to
keep the original model. Now, when we do
this, the precision will slightly
decrease from the original model.
However, we get way more space and we'll
end up getting a better output actually
because we have more room to be able to
train the adapter layers. I'm not going
to get into the mechanics too much. I
don't want to teach you all of the, you
know, advanced computer science and all
that's going into this and the
mathematics, but the basic idea is that
QLoRA, exact same thing as LoRA, just a
compressed version, slightly less
precision, but overall for almost all of
us we need to use this because we don't
have 100 GPUs sitting in our computer
and an unlimited amount of space to
train these models. Okay, so hopefully
that makes sense and I want to keep
going and talk about fine-tuning versus
RAG, which is a common misconception.
But first, if you're interested in AI,
you're going to want to hear about this.
Quick heads-up. Everything you're
watching right now was generated with
HeyGen, my sponsor for this video. Now,
this isn't me on camera, it's my digital
twin avatar, and this whole ad was made
from a script. Now, here's why that
matters. Normally, I write the code,
then burn 3 hours filming, flubbing
lines, and relighting the entire room
just to explain it. And if I get one
line wrong, I'm shooting the whole thing
again.
Now, with HeyGen, I recorded one
15-second clip one time. That built my
digital twin. Now, I just paste the
script, and this AI video generator
makes the videos. Same face, same voice,
no camera, no reshoots. And it's not
stiff or robotic. It's fast, the
lipstick is real, and the gestures
actually look like me. If I want to
change a line, I just change the text,
not the whole take.
Now, here's the part that got me,
though. It'll translate this exact video
into 175-plus languages in my own voice
with the lip sync match. So, the same
explainer can reach people who normally
never watch it. And if this looks filmed
to you, that's the point. You've been
watching the demo the entire time. No
studio, no crew, just one script. Try
HeyGen for free with the link in the
description, and go make a video without
ever getting on camera.
Okay, so let's dive into fine-tuning
versus rag quick, and I promise we're
almost at the demo. Now, a lot of people
believe that fine-tuning cannot teach an
LLM new information. They think that rag
is always the way to go, and that you
need rag for something like domain
expertise. Now, this is actually not the
case, it's a common misconception, and
the difference between rag and
fine-tuning is that rag will allow you
to retrieve real, up-to-date data and
feed that into the prompt for a model.
So, what you're doing is effectively
injecting facts or information or fresh
data into the prompt so the model can
reason based on that. This is a
different approach from fine-tuning.
Fine-tuning actually adjust the weights
itself, right? By adding these lower
adapter layers, so the model itself will
reply differently without you needing to
do anything to the prompt. Okay, so
let's quickly talk about the hardware
requirements here, which are important
to understand. Now, technically, no
matter what hardware you have, as long
as you have a computer, you are able to
follow along here. However, if you're on
Windows, it's going to be best if you
have a moderated Nvidia GPU, ideally
something with 12 GB of VRAM or more.
And if you're on Mac, you have a
relatively modern M-series MacBook with
as much RAM as you can possibly get. If
you have, for example, 24, 32, 64 GB of
RAM, and we're talking M3, M4, M5, you
know, Pro, Max, whatever, that's going
to be pretty good performance for what
we're about to do. That said, no matter
what you have, feel free to play along.
It's just the speeds you're going to get
will be probably lower than what you see
me getting here. And the important thing
is that if you're on Windows, you want
to look at how much video memory you
have on your GPU. And if you're on Mac,
you want to look at how much unified
memory you have, because that's going to
dictate the size of the models that you
can fine-tune. Now, for some reason you
have really low-end hardware, you can
actually use a free Google Colab
notebook that comes from Unsloth. I
think they have it in their
documentation. I believe there's a Colab
notebook that they link to somewhere
inside of here, and you can train it in
the cloud using a free GPU that comes
from Google. I'm not going to go through
that process, but for you guys, you can
do that, and it's kind of a similar flow
to what I'm going to do here. Okay, so
with that said, let's install Unsloth
Studio, and let's set everything up, and
hopefully you have a basis of what
fine-tuning actually is. So, to set this
up depends on the operating system that
you're on. What I'm going to do is just
go here to the documentation. We're
going to go to get started. And sorry, I
should have to search through and find
it. We're going to find the installation
commands. Now, what we're going to do
here is just open up a terminal, so let
me put one on the right-hand side of my
screen. If you're on Mac or Windows,
it'll will a different command. So, on
Mac or Linux, it's going to be this
command right here. Again, I'll link
this in the description, but you can
find it right from the main page if you
scroll down here. And if you're on
Windows, it's going to be this one here.
So, what I'm going to do is just paste
the command, go ahead and press on
enter, and it should start setting
everything up for you. This will take a
few minutes to install, so be patient.
And once it's done, I'll be right back.
Okay, so once the install is finished,
it should prompt you to start Unsloth
Studio. You can start it with the
command that it shows you right here, or
you can just type yes, and it will
automatically start it. So, I'm going to
go Y, and it will start. If that doesn't
work, just copy the launch command right
here and run it in your terminal. So,
now it should be running, and what you
can do is you can go to localhost port
8888. And if you do that, you should be
prompted in your browser to a uh Unsloth
Studio UI. Now, in my case, it's still
loading up. You can see it's still
running here and enabling everything, so
it's going to take a second, but we'll
wait for it to boot up, and you can see
that it's now here. Now, you need to
have this terminal window running in the
background in order for this to work.
So, you can just minimize this, but make
sure you don't exit out of the terminal,
otherwise it will shut down the studio.
So, again, anytime you want to run this,
you're going to open up the terminal,
and you're just going to run this
command right here, or you can just
rerun the install command, and then just
press yes, and it should boot it up for
you. Again, I'm going to minimize this,
keep it running in the background, and
now we're in the studio. Now, from the
studio, the first thing that we want to
do if we want to start with fine-tuning
is we need to pick a model to download
that we want to fine-tune. So, what you
can do is go to this model selector up
here at the top. You also can go to hub.
Now, when you go here, you're going to
have the ability to search through
different models. And if you look at the
model selector, if you go to the chat
interface, it will show you any models
that you already have downloaded. You
can see that I have a bunch of them cuz
I've done a lot of local AI stuff, but
for most of you, probably don't have
any. Now, the important thing to note
here is that you cannot use a GGUF model
for fine-tuning. You need a model that's
in an MLK format or a safe tensors
format. So, if you see a bunch of models
from like LM Studio, for example, that
you have downloaded and they say GGUF,
you're not going to be able to fine-tune
those. You need a different model
format. So, just keep that in mind,
okay? So, what we're going to do is just
go to hub, and I'm going to explain to
you how you can select the model that
you want to fine-tune. Okay, so once
we're on this hub page, we need to
quickly discuss how we can actually find
a model that we can fine-tune. Now, I
have a quick kind of guide here, so let
me explain. So, if you have 6 GB of VRAM
or unified memory, you can probably
fine-tune a model with 3 to 4 billion
parameters. If you have 10 GB, you can
do something with 7 or 8 billion
parameters, which is a really good sweet
spot. If you have 16 to 20 GB, you can
do something with 12 to 14 billion. And
if you have more, then you can go up to
your 27, 35, 70 billion parameter
models, but those are quite large and
honestly don't require fine-tuning or
don't benefit from it as much. In most
cases, I found you can get really good
performance out of 8 billion parameter
models. So, if you're capable of doing
that, great. If not, you will have to go
to a smaller model. And picking the
models, you can consult with Claude,
ChatGPT based on the specific hardware
you have to find the current best ones,
cuz I'm sure it will change after this
video is out, that you should fine-tune.
Regardless, if you want a relatively
safe model to fine-tune that you can do
with mid-level hardware, what we're
going to do is go to the hub. We're
going to change this to say fine-tune
ready, super important. And then we're
going to search for Llama 3.1.
Now, specifically, what we're going to
look for is this model right here. I
already have it downloaded, that's why
it's not showing up. Llama 3.1 8 billion
instruct Unsloth BNB 4-bit. And you can
see that it's 6 GB in size itself when
you download it. This is a quantized
version of the Llama 3.1 8 billion
instruct model. So, it's already shrunk
down to a significantly smaller size,
which just saves us the time from
downloading it. You can have it shrunk
automatically, but it's It's better we
download this one directly. So, this is
a model that most of you can follow
along with. Download it on your machine
if you want to just use this. If you
want to use something else again, go
crazy, search for it, but just make sure
that when you search for it, you have it
under fine-tune ready. It needs to be
fine-tunable, and then it's a size that
fits on your machine. So, you're looking
at your VRAM or the amount of unified
memory depending on your device. Now, I
also just have some quick info for you
when you pick these models. First, pick
the instruct model, not the base model.
You can read the reasons why, but
instruct is already trained to follow
the directions. It will give you a much
better result. If you can, grab the BNB
4-bit variant, which is already shrunk
down and pre-quantized for the QLoRA,
um, what is it, fine-tuning. If they
don't have it, don't worry, you can have
it shrunk automatically, and then get a
safe tensors version, not this GGUF
format, which is designed for inference
and running models already, not for
fine-tuning.
Okay. So, now that we have the model
downloaded, okay, so we've got it on our
device. If we go to chat, we should be
able to see it. So, you can see I have
this, you know, Unsloth BNB 4-bit
version, and I can just load it up. So,
I just select the model, and we'll wait
a second, and we can directly chat with
it inside of this user interface.
Obviously, make sure the model works
before we spend the time to actually
fine-tune it, um, and I'll just wait for
it to load, and we'll chat with it.
Okay, so it took a second, but it's
loaded. So, if I type with it now, and I
say something like hello world, you can
see that I get a response, okay? And
then, you can just start using it
directly from the chat interface. Now,
that's great, but of course, we want to
fine-tune it. So, to fine-tune it, you
can go to this train tab here, and I'm
going to show you how to do this. But
before we can fine-tune it, we need a
dataset or some data to fine-tune it
with. And what I want to do is discuss
what that data should actually look like
so you can understand the process of
fine-tuning. Now, effectively, what we
want in our dataset is we want to have
an instruction, we want to have input,
and we want to have output. Okay, these
are three columns that we want to have
contained in whatever data set we're
going to use to fine-tune. Now, with
these three columns, that will give the
model enough information to start
learning the patterns in our data and
training these Laura adapter layers so
that they can be specific to our
to our domain, right? Or to whatever it
is that we want it to do. So, if you
look at the right-hand side of my
screen, you can see an example. We have
instructions and and then we have an
output, okay? And the idea is that we're
going to pass a bunch of examples of
this to the model when we train it, so
it can learn, okay, based on this input,
what should the output be? But, it will
be flexible and dynamic enough to be
able to handle unique situations, which
means we don't need tens of thousands of
different examples, we just need a few
hundred or a few thousand. So, for
example, if you have, you know, 300 to
1,000 rows, it will shift the tone and
the format. If you have 5,000, 10,000,
15,000 examples, you can teach a real
legitimate skill to this model that it's
going to be better at performing it. In
my case, I think I'm going to use 1,100
rows, and you will see what results we
get and how drastic the behavior
actually can be. And the reason you see
this input as optional here is that you
don't need to provide an explicit input
kind of example or prompt, it's enough
just to provide an instruction and an
output, but if you do provide an example
input, you will get better results. So,
effectively, you just have example
conversations, okay? Now, there's lots
of other different types of data sets
you can make, but this is the easiest to
go with, and you can actually have AI
generate this for you, which I'll show
you in a second. So, just to give you a
deeper look here, I'm not going to use
this exact data set, but you can see row
12, we have a policy row, right? Handle
refund request, here's the input, here's
the output. Answer a discount question,
do you have student pricing? We do,
student pricing is this. Troubleshoot a
crash report, boom, input, output, you
get the idea. So, effectively, what
we're doing is we're trying to teach the
model this new information, so it gets
baked into the weights. Okay, now the
question becomes, how do we generate or
get this data? So, I'm going to show you
the data set that I'm going to use, and
then I'm going to show you how you can
make it, and there's multiple different
ways. So, this is the data set that I'm
going to use. You'll notice that the
instruction is always the same. However,
I adjust the input and the output values
because this is kind of how I want it to
work. Now, I myself am learning
Indonesian right now, and I only know a
few hundred words. So, I'm like a pretty
basic speaker. So, what I want to do is
I want to train an LLM to be able to
chat with me in Indonesian, but only to
use words that I'm familiar with and in
a format that I'm used to practicing so
that I can progress without being, you
know, overwhelmed. So, effectively, this
is going to seem confusing if you don't
speak Indonesian, but we have a bunch of
input, which are words that I know, and
a bunch of output, which are also words
that I know. And the way that I
generated this is that I just went to
Claude, and I said, "Hey, these are all
the words that I know in Indonesian,"
and I pasted like 300 words have in my
kind of vocabulary application. And I
said, "Can you generate a data set that
looks something like this, right, for
me?" And actually, I guess how many rows
do we have? We have, sorry, so we have
3,000 in this one that I can pass to
Unsloth Studio. And then it generated
this 3,000 list JSONL data set for me
that has instruction, input, output. So,
that's like the simplest version of
making the data set. You just say, "Hey,
I'm training a model in Unsloth Studio.
Go to Claude. Generate a data set for me
based on XYZ, right?" can do that. And
in this case, it worked like super well.
However, Unsloth Studio itself has a way
to make your own data sets using
something called a recipe. So, I'm going
to show you an example recipe and kind
of how you can create it because, to be
honest, it is a little bit confusing,
and do it directly inside of Unsloth
using AI generation.
Okay, so if you go to this recipes tab,
you'll be able to make a new recipe.
Now, when you do this, you can start
from a learning recipe, or you can start
from empty. Now, the learning recipes
for me were a little bit confusing to go
through, so I made my own that I think
is much more clear, and I'm going to
show you how it works. And then again, I
promise we're going to get to the
training, but I got to go through these
steps so that you guys have everything
you need and you're not going to be
completely lost. So, what you can do
here if you want to follow along with me
is you can make a new recipe. Now, also,
keep in mind, you can use an existing
data set from Hugging Face if there's
one that you want to use. So, for
example, if you go here, you can select
Hugging Face, and you can scroll through
and there's tons of data sets that you
can use. Um the issue with this is that
most of the time they're not for your
exact domain or your exact use case, so
it doesn't really make a lot of sense to
use those, right? But if there's a
public data set you want to use, just go
ahead and use one. You can just select
it from Hugging Face. But again, I'm
showing you how to make your own cuz I
think that's more valuable. So, from
here, you're going to go new recipe,
start empty, and then what I'm going to
do is just go into my existing recipe so
I can show you what it looks like. So,
when you open up a recipe here, you
should first of all be able to change
the name. So, I'm calling mine Indo or
Indonesian recipe.
And then you can press this plus button
here, and you can start adding notes.
Now, for most of us, what we probably
want to do is we want to start with some
kind of seed data. Now, the seed data
could be a document, for example. It
could be a PDF with company information
that you have, with your refund
policies, with a Q&A. It could be a CSV
file that has a bunch of words in it. It
could be whatever. I don't know what
you're going to try to fine-tune, so
it's hard for me to guess. But you can
see that you can bring in a GitHub repo,
a CSV or JSON file. You can bring in a
Hugging Face data set itself. You can
bring in a document like a PDF, and you
can parse it into individual rows. So,
what I did is I've brought in a CSV or a
JSON file. So, I went to the plus, I
went to source data, I went to CSV or
JSON file, right? And I dragged it in.
Now, it's not letting me do that cuz I
already have one, but you can see
that what I did here is I selected a
file. Now, it's going to make me select
it again, but the file that I selected,
let me find it, is this vocabulary seed,
which I'm going to load and show you
what it looks like. And again, I had
Claude generate this for me.
Now, this is just a list of all of the
Indonesian words that I know. Now, I
actually got this from a platform that I
used to practice Indonesian, but you can
see that I have Indonesian, English,
category, example, and then example
English. So, I just have five very
simple CSV columns. And if again, I open
this up in VS Code here, let me show
you. You can see like it's pretty
straightforward. I have what? 276 rows.
So, I don't have anything crazy
complicated. And again, you can make
this super easily with AI. Or if you
have some existing data you want to
bring in, perfect, bring it in. So, I
have this kind of existing data. Now,
it's not currently in a format that
works, right? Because the format that I
need for fine-tuning is I need
instruction and output, or instruction,
input, output. That's what I need in
order for this to work. So, what I did
is I've kind of loaded this in. And if I
want, I can remove some of these
columns, but I want to keep all of them.
So, I've loaded in this JSON data. It's
now here.
Next, what I've done is I've said,
"Okay, there's a few different types of
kind of tasks that I want to try to
generate for my fine-tuning data. I want
to be able to translate English to
Indonesian. I want to be able to kind of
like generally chat. I want to know what
the meaning of an Indonesian word is in
English. I want to be able to generate a
quiz. I want to make a new word. I want
to do a correction. I want to do like
daily practice." So, what I've done is
I've brought in this category note. Now,
the way that I did that is I went to
generate fields, and I went to category.
And notice that there's a bunch of stuff
here. Like you can generate a random
number. You can generate a yes or no
value. And what I've done,
okay, is I've said, "These are kind of
the different values I want to have."
And then these are the weights that I
want to associate to each column. So, I
want to have 27% of the categories be
this. I want to have 23% be chat. I want
to have 5% be correction. Okay? So, what
I'm saying here is I want to generate a
new data set. That's what I'm going to
do in this recipe. In this data set, I
want to have different categories of
kind of example prompts. And then I want
27% of those to be this category, 23% to
be this category. You'll see what I mean
as we keep going through, but I'm making
a distribution that will kind of
randomly select categories as I go
through this flow. Okay? So, that's what
I've done with category. If I wanted
subcategory, I can add that. Now, what
I've done next is I put in an
instruction. Now, this node what I did
here was I used a formula. Now, formula
is just an expression where you can
combine variables together, and you can
just bring in a normal string.
So, what I did is I pasted a prompt in
here where I said, "You are Carto, Tim's
personal Indonesian tutor. Speak simple
Indonesian using only vocabulary Tim
already knows." And this is just that
starting instruction prompt, okay? So,
this is the instruction every time. So,
I've just said, "Hey, I want to have
this be called instruction. I want the
output type to be a string." And I'm
just storing the instruction here.
That's it. And I want this to be in my
final data set, so I didn't uncheck this
box right here, which keeps it out of
the final data set. If I wanted this
just to be used as like an intermediate
value, then I would select this.
Okay. Again, I promise I'm going to
explain it more, but this is just like a
little bit complicated, so I got to go
through it step by step.
Okay, so we start with some seed data,
right? We connect that to some task. We
connect that to some instruction. And
then what I do is I use an AI generation
step. Now, this is where this becomes
useful, because what I can do is
generate using AI this data set that I
then want to fine-tune my LLM model
with.
So, what I've done
is I've added a Let me find it here.
Model provider and connection. So, I
just brought in this provider here.
When I bring in this provider, what I
can do is I can configure it, and I can
choose what model I want to use for
generating this data set for me. Because
effectively, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to tell the model, "Hey, based on
these words, based on this instruction,
generate a sample input, instruction,
and output, and help me create a data
set that I can then fine-tune my model
with." That's what this recipe thing is
doing. So, I'm using a local model,
which means, "Hey, I'm just going to use
the local model that I actually have
already on my own computer." But, if I
want to connect to OpenAI, for example,
or Anthropic, I just put in the
endpoint, and I put in the API key, and
I can now use a close source model,
right? Which is going to be faster to
generate the data set for me. But, I'm
going with local model, which just means
use whatever one is currently loaded.
Okay. So, let me just delete this one.
So, once [snorts] I have that, I can
then connect this to a model config. So,
if we go here,
let me find a few. Uh AI generation.
This is a model preset, so you can see
this model preset right here. For the
model preset, provider is just local
model, so we're just using whatever it's
connected to. And for the model itself,
you can choose what you want to use. So,
you can see that here, choose local
model, I can pick this Hugging Face
model, right? And then load that in
there, and this is now the one that I'm
going to use, and I can adjust the
temperature, which is the randomness.
Okay. So, I've brought in the model
provider. I then connect the model
provider to another node that I have
here. Let me show it to you. This node
is the AI structured data generator,
which is what I would recommend that you
use. But, you'll notice if you look
here, there's a lot of other ones you
can use, like AI score, AI code,
whatever, AI text. So, you can create
something.
That's what we're doing, right? We're
trying to create values for the data
set. So, for this, let me configure it
for you.
I called it make row. I'm keeping this
data, so I didn't select this. For the
model preset, I'm just using the preset
I created above. Notice it's
automatically connected. It's called
model one, right? And then, I've given
it a really long prompt that explains to
it the examples that I want it to
generate. So, I say, right? You are
generating one training example for
fine-tuning a A Indonesian tutor for
Tim, a beginner. Hard rule, every
Indonesian word in the example may only
come from the known words list.
Okay? English text is unrestricted,
never use any other Indonesian word with
one exception, if the row type is new
word, use exactly one word from the new
words pool. Okay? So that we can
introduce a bit of, you know, new stuff.
Now, what I do is I start embedding
variables in here that comes from what I
had before. So, I have the task type,
right? And the task type was generated,
if we look here, as this task type
field. Okay? Then, let's keep going.
I have the
uh rows vocabulary card, Indonesian is
equal to English. So, I'm using some of
that data from the seed data that I had.
The card example is example, and then
example English. And then you can see
that I said, "Write the example for this
row type, chat." Boom. I want you to do
this. If it's translate, I want you to
do this. If it's quiz, I want you to do
this. If it's new word, I want you to do
this. You get the idea, okay? And then
if we keep going here, it says style
rule, short and friendly. And then here
all the known words that I know. So, the
idea is I'm saying, "Okay, I'm
effectively going to loop through all of
the seed data that I have. I'm going to
generate a type for the seed data. I'm
going to just have my instruction. And
then I'm going to make a new row. And
the new row that I'm going to make,
right? If we look at it here, is going
to now, if we scroll down, have this
output format. And I've put a JSON
format that says, "Hey, I want to have
input, right? So, property input, this
is type string. And I want to have, let
me move this back,
output. This is type string, required
input output." So, I'm saying, "Generate
an input for me and an output for me
based on the prompt that I gave."
Hopefully that makes sense. I know it's
a little bit confusing when you go
through this recipe builder, but I'm
using AI to generate the data for me.
So, again, we bring in our seed data,
task type, instruction, you get the
idea. This is a basic example, there's a
lot of other stuff you can do, and they
have some other examples you can look
at, but I'm kind of generating all of
these training rows, and that's what
this is mean meaning to do. And if you
don't want to do it this way, you can
just ask an AI model to generate it for
you. Again, you don't need that many. If
you have a few thousand rows, that's
enough to have really good fine-tuning.
I think the main thing to understand
here is that you want to have input
instruction output. If you have those
three fields in your training data,
that's what you need. Okay? So, from
here, what we can do is press check. If
we press check, we can just verify to
make sure the workflow looks good. And
then we're going to do a test run. So,
I'm just going to do two records for
right now, and go check, and then again,
two, and test run. And when I do test
run, what this should do, so let's start
the test run, is it will bring up a
progress bar for us, and it should run
through this flow, and generate some
examples for us. So, we can just make
sure the examples look logical before we
move to the next step. Okay, so you can
see that it generated this for us, and
if I look at the columns, or sorry, if I
look at the raw or data, that's what I
want to look at. You can see we have
Indonesian, English, category, example,
example English, and then we have
instruction, and then make row. And for
make row, we have the input and we have
the Let's look here, output. Okay? Says,
"Apa bahasa Indonesia untuk brush
teeth?" What is it How do you say brush
teeth in Indonesian? What is it saying?
And then, boom, this is how you say it,
okay? Hello, whatever whatever whatever,
and then this is the output. And these
are all words that I know, okay? So,
this is now the example data that was
created. We verify it, we make sure it
makes sense. Okay, I can save it. And
then what I can do is go back to the
editor, and now I can go run. And this
time, when I want to do a full run, I
can press full run, I can give this a
data set Indo words, and then decide how
many records I want to generate. So, do
I want to generate a thousand rows, ten
thousand rows, whatever, and then decide
do I want to generate a thousand rows,
ten thousand rows, whatever. I can
enable batching, I can do throughput,
retries, whatever. So, let's say we want
to just generate a fifty row data set,
then I can start the full run. And same
thing, I can wait here for this to run,
and I can see the progress as it
generates it. And you can see before, I
generated some previous data sets like
this one had three thousand rows. I'm
not going to wait for all of that to
finish cuz it is going to take a fair
amount of time to do on my computer, but
this is how you generate the data set.
So, let's wait at least just for this
one to be done and then I'll move to the
next step. Okay, so one thing you'll
notice when this is generating that it's
going to show you the rate, so the
number of records it's doing per second.
In my case, it's super slow cuz I'm just
using a local model on my own computer,
and you can see that it's going to take
332 seconds, which is like 5 minutes or
something um to run, right? That's the
estimated time. One thing to notice that
it's not going to give you live
up-to-date progress. It's going to be
polling and give you progress over a
certain period. So, in this case, it
says, "Hey, I'm going to give you
progress every five entries." So, if
you're unsure if something's happening,
open this overview, look in the
terminal, and you can see
that every time it generates 5, 10, 100,
500 uh entries, whatever, then it will
update you. So, don't think it's frozen
cuz sometimes it is just super slow. And
again, if you want this to be way
faster, change the model provider here
so that you're not using um a local
provider and you're using a third-party
provider like OpenAI or something. And
it's cost going to cost you a little bit
of money to generate that if you use
this type of recipe. Again, I found
better results just directly doing it
through Claude, um but we'll wait for
this to finish just so you can see how
the recipe works in Unsloth. Okay, so it
just finished here. It took a long time.
It was like lagging my whole computer,
but if I go to the recipe, you can see
we've got 50 words and it's generated
the uh make row column, which is what
we're looking for, which was the input
output. You get the idea. So, now that
we have this, it's time to actually
fine-tune and start training. Now, to do
that, we're going to go to this train
tab here. We're going to select the
model that we want to fine-tune, so I'm
going to go with this 3.1 billion
instruct Unsloth BNB 4-bit model, but
pick whatever one you downloaded, okay?
For the method, we're going to go with
QLoRA. You can use more if you want, but
this is going to take a long time if you
go to ones that are higher than the
QLoRA, so I recommend staying with the
4-bit. Then, for the data set, either
select a Hugging Face data set or go to
local. When you go to local, you should
see the data sets that you created in
the recipes tab, and you can select
them. However, if you want instead, you
can upload a CSV file. So, you can see I
have the data set that I showed you guys
before, so we can view it, right? And
you can see that it looks like
instruction, input, output. If that's
the case, we can just select this, and
we can go with that if it's already
created for us. However, if I select one
of the ones that I created, so like
recipe Indo data set here. Okay, this is
one that I created previously. You're
going to notice that if I go to view
data set here, then it shows me that it
could not auto-detect column rows for
these. So, what we can do here is we can
use this AI assistant to assign the
rows, or we can go here and specify
them. So, we can say system, user,
assistant, system, right? Whatever. We
can set all these different rows, so
that it understands what we should
actually use for the input, output,
instruction. Again, it's a little bit
different here because it's a slightly
different format, but you get the idea.
So, if I go with AI assistant here, it
can analyze the data set, and then it
will automatically mark the columns for
us, and then we can use that for the
fine-tuning. When we're selecting this,
right? The system is essentially the
instruction, user is the input, and then
assistant is the output, okay? So, when
we're marking these, that's how we want
to do it. One thing to keep in mind is
make row, we really should split this
into two separate rows, which we could
do in the um what do you call it? Uh
recipe as well. Make an expression, so
we have two separate output rows that
get generated, one for input, one for
output. I didn't do that cuz I'm not
actually using this as the data set for
fine-tuning, but we would want to do
that so that we could then mark the user
and assistant properly, and then for the
instruction, we would mark this as
system, which is effectively the system
prompt. And you can see that it's
determined, hey, instruction is system.
So, I'm not going to let it go through
that cuz I'm just going to use the data
set that I already know, which is this
one here, Indonesian Tutor. Again, when
I view the data set, because it's in
Indonesia or in instruction input
output, it knows how we should
categorize these, and we are good to go.
So, from there, what we're going to do
is go over to parameters. So, once we
have the data set selected, for the
project name, give it a name, I'm going
to go Indo Training 2. For the number of
steps, you can change this to be epochs.
I recommend that you just start with one
epoch, especially if you have simple
data, and see the result that you get.
However, standard best practice is to go
with three, so not 13, but three. Um if
you have a lot of data, so the more data
you have, the more epochs you want to go
with, but typically for simple stuff, if
you do more than one, um you're going to
have a loss value that goes down very
quickly, which you're going to see in a
second. Now, there's a bunch of other
settings you can adjust, like rank,
alpha, dropout, um LoRA adapters, hyper
parameters. To be honest, if you're a
beginner and you don't know what you're
doing, just leave them all exactly the
same. The only thing to adjust is the
epoch, which will directly determine the
amount of time this is going to take to
train. Once you have set this,
go here to start training, and it will
start fine-tuning and training the model
for you. Now, depending on the number of
rows that you have in your data set, the
size of the base model, and the number
of steps or epoch settings that you have
here, that's going to determine how long
this will take to run for you. So, we're
going to let this run, it's taking a
second here, and you can see that it's
loaded the model weights, and it's about
to spin everything up. And if we want to
see the history, we can go here, and we
can see the progress of its training.
Now, we also can go to the terminal,
just to verify that all of this is
working. If you want to see the output,
it will take a second to actually start
training, and then once it starts
training, it's going to show us a bunch
of data that I will quickly go through,
and then we'll fast forward to when it's
finished. All right, so we can see that
it's in the process of training here. We
can see how much VRAM it's using,
temperature, power, all of this, and we
can view the training loss, the gradient
norm, and the learning rate. Now,
quickly, learning rate, this is going to
gradually decrease over time. The idea
is that the more that we train the
model, the less that we want it to learn
new information over time, so we're just
making small adjustments. The training
loss is the main graph that you want to
look at, and effectively what we're
going to expect to happen is over time
the loss value to decrease. The loss is
effectively going to tell us what the
accuracy is and how well the model is
predicting the next tokens based on the
examples that we've given it. Now, in
this case, I have a very simple data
set. It's just language the model's
already very good at. It already knows
the format. It's template based, so it's
really easy for the model to learn this,
and you'll see the loss drastically
drops down. So, we start really high,
and immediately at step 10 we've already
dropped below this value, which means
that it's already performing extremely
well. So, what we're going to do is pay
attention to this and hope that the loss
continues to go down, and as soon as you
see that kind of sharp decline, you know
that you've effectively trained the
model accurately and that it's going to
work relatively well. Now, I'm not going
to go through this whole training
process here because I don't need to
wait for it cuz I already have one
trained that I can show you, but the
idea is you're going to wait for this to
finish. It will show you the ETA, the
steps, tokens, all of this kind of
stuff. It will show you all of the
entries that it's gone through here in
the data set, whatever, and then you can
just adjust the settings if you want uh
in terms of viewing it, and you can stop
it. Don't worry too much about the
gradient norm. If you want to check that
out, you can ask an AI model to explain
it to you, but generally the loss is
what we're looking at, and you can see
that again cuz my data set is really
simple. It drops off super quickly, and
as long as you see the loss dropping
below one, then that typically means
that it's performing fairly well, at
least as it's evaluating itself in the
training. Okay, so what I'm going to do
is stop this for now. I'm just going to
cancel it cuz I don't need that anymore,
and I'm now going to go and show you the
fine-tuned model that I have. Now,
again, I already trained this before the
video so we didn't have to wait for it,
and to find this I can go to on device,
and I can search for my fine-tuned
model, and you can see that I have a
fine-tuned model here that I'm going to
load up, and I'm going to show you how
we can compare it to the base model to
ensure it's working properly. Okay, so
you can see that it's loaded up now, and
I can start chatting with it directly.
But, what I can also do is if I press
this plus button, I can go more, and I
can go compare chat. Now, when I go
compare chat, what it's going to do is
compare the base model to the fine-tuned
version, so we can see the response that
we get from both, and if we want to
adjust any of the settings here, like
the temperature, top P, whatever, we can
do that directly from here, and also
input a system prompt. So, for example,
we may say something like hello, apa
kabar,
which is hello, how are you in
Indonesian. And let's see the response
that we get. Okay, and you can see on
our side, we get this is the fine-tuned
side, I get words that I actually know.
Every word here I know. I can translate
the sentence for you. This one, not so
much. You can see it immediately gives
me a bunch of Indonesian words that are
probably still simple, but beyond my
comprehension and understanding, which
makes it significantly more difficult
for me to continue this conversation.
Now, let's do another example. Can you
tell me what the word alone means?
Okay, and let's continue, and it says in
Indonesian, kata alone dalam whatever,
right? Like, I don't know what this
means cuz I cannot fully read all this
Indonesian. And here, it says alone
equals sama canto dia pergi sama, he
goes alone, okay? And then it gives me
the explanation. So, because of the
fine-tuning, now I have essentially an
Indonesian kind of teacher that I can
chat with, where when I ask it
something, it understands that I'm a
beginner, it needs to use basic words,
and I can have a significantly better
conversation. Let's do something else.
How would you say I want to go work out
today in Indonesian?
Okay, and let's see what we get. And
again, it's speaking to me in
Indonesian. It's not even speaking to me
in English. And here, it gives me the
direct translation, which is exactly
what I'm looking for, and this is a very
simple way to say this, compared to what
it gave me right here or right here,
which is much more complicated and I
don't know.
So, that's the fine-tuning. So, now if
you were happy with the fine-tuning, we
could export the model, so I could go
here, select my model, and export it to
a GGUF model, which I can use in
something like Ollama. I can do a full
16-bit inference model. I can do a Lora
version. You get the idea, and I can use
this in pretty much any tool that I
want, share it with someone, upload it
to Hugging Face, like you can see here.
And you guys get the idea, we can export
it and use it from there. Okay. That was
a lot of content. That was a full course
on using Unsloth Studio. I know it took
a long time, and there was a lot to
explain, but I hope you guys found value
in this video. If you did, make sure to
leave a like, subscribe to the channel,
and I will see you in the next one.
>> [music]
[music]